Nicholas J. Wilson

[version date 2024.06]

nj.wilson@outlook.com njwsn.github.io

PROFILE

Economist and researcher focusing on development and political economy. My research interests center on fragility and social cohesion, with a geographic focus on Africa and the Middle East. Headed consulting engagements for UNDP, UNHCR, World Bank, IRC, IFRC, AMF, among others. Formerly based in China, Germany, Kenya, the Netherlands, Russia, UK; now South Sudan/Turkey.

EDUCATION

Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München

Munich, DE

Economics, MSc Grade: 1.14, Sehr Gut (Top ranked student)

2020-23

• Visiting student: Higher School of Economics - Moscow.

University of Warwick

Coventry, GB

Economics, BSc (Hons) Grade: 70, First Class

2013-17

Visiting student: University of Amsterdam.

EXPERIENCE

Forcier Consulting

Juba, SS/Istanbul, TR

Research Manager

2022-24

- Managed an office of 20 full-time staff conducting mixed methods research across South Sudan.
- Fielded surveys, focus groups, and interviews, and analyzed development programs and policies.
- Negotiated with clients, trained researchers, supervised data collection, managed project budgets.
- Advised on political economy and logistics of program implementation in the country and region.

University of Massachusetts (UMass) Amherst

Remote

Research Assistant

2021-22

- Research Assistant (RA) for Prof. Lucy Xiaolu Wang, conducting research in health economics.
- Activities included literature reviews, data cleaning and analysis, managed several junior RAs.

Max Planck Institute for Innovation and Competition

Munich, DE

Research Assistant

2020-21

- RA for Prof. Lucy Xiaolu Wang, conducting research in health and innovation economics.
- Activities included literature reviews, data cleaning and analysis, management of a junior RA.

United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)

Nairobi, KE

Communications Consultant

2019-20

- Served as comms & partnerships focal point for UNDP's Governance & Inclusive Growth portfolio.
- Conducted fieldwork and participated in M&E missions to more than 20 counties across Kenya.

OC&C Strategy Consultants

London, GB

Associate Consultant

2018-19

- Strategy, market research, and commercial due diligence consulting projects for clients in EMEA.
- Built market forecasts, visualized spatial data, analyzed surveys, interviewed industry players.

Magic Panda International 能猫国际集团 Shanghai, CN International E-Commerce Intern Winter 2017

Rothschild & Co London, GB Investment Banking Summer Intern Summer 2016

Lazard London, GB Summer 2015

Investment Banking Summer Intern

SELECTED CONSULTANCIES

World Bank Group 2024 Country Opinion Survey – South Sudan (2024)

Contracted by the World Bank to administer a multi-format survey to a cross-section of different WBG stakeholders across South Sudan to assess programmatic challenges and opportunities.

Survey of SSRC Branches Income Generating Activities (2024)

Contracted by the South Sudan Red Cross (SSRC) to undertake a study of challenges and opportunities to undertaking income generating activities at 15 of their branches across South Sudan.

Maternal and Child Health Baseline Study in Aweil East (2024)

Contracted by the International Rescue Committee (IRC) to design a methodology for and undertake a quantitative survey of maternal health and newborn care indicators in Aweil East, South Sudan.

Scoping Study on Agriculture and Food Security Value Chains in South Sudan (2024)

Contracted by Norweigan Church Aid (NCA) to undertake a qualitative analysis of the landscape, challenges, and opportunities for agriculture value chain addition in 5 states of South Sudan.

Education Research in Conflict and Protracted Crises (ERICC) in South Sudan (2023-24)

Contracted by IRC to synthesize and explore education in emergencies research priorities for South Sudan through a literature review, mixed methods fieldwork, and workshops with key stakeholders.

Third-Party Monitoring of South Sudan 2022/23 LLIN Distribution Campaign (2023)

Contracted by the Against Malaria Foundation (AMF) to monitor planning, distribution, and verification activities for a national campaign to distribute 5.4m mosquito nets in 7 states of South Sudan.

Implementation of the UNHCR Forced Displaced Survey (FDS) in South Sudan (2022-23)

Contracted by UNHCR to implement a major global survey initiative in South Sudan assessing living conditions of IDPs, refugees, asylum seekers and returnees in camps and host communities.

CRC South Sudan: Healthy Bodies, Healthy Minds Qualitative Evaluation (2022)

Contracted by the Canadian Red Cross (CRC) to conduct a project evaluation, comprising focus group discussions (FGDs) and draw, write, and tell (DWT) workshops in Warrap, South Sudan.

UNDP Support to Devolved Governance in Kenya: Transformational Stories (2020)

Contracted by UNDP to contribute analyses and edit a narrative review of their support to implementation of the devolution process across Kenya, which included conducting fieldwork in 6 counties.

PUBLICATIONS

U.S. State Approaches to Cannabis Licensing (with Lucy Xiaolu Wang) [2022]

International Journal of Drug Policy (IJDP), 106, 103755 [IJDP]; MPI Research Paper [SSRN] Analysis of different state-level licensing and taxation policies for the US legal cannabis market.

WORKS IN PROGRESS

ERICC: An Evidence-driven Education in Emergencies Research Agenda for South Sudan (with Ioanna Wagner-Tsoni, Ceaser Taban, and Maartje Schots)

Synthesis and description of education in emergencies research priorities for South Sudan.

ODI Working Paper: Political Economy of the South Sudan Education System (with Olha Homonchuk, Alexandra Fortacz, and Tim Kelsall)

Education-focused political economy analysis based on desk research and key informant interviews.

Conflict's Long Shadow: Evidence on Education in Emergencies in South Sudan (with Ioanna Wagner-Tsoni, Ceaser Taban, and Maartje Schots)

Systematic literature review identifying education in emergencies evidence gaps in South Sudan.

Hate Thy Neighbor? Conflict, Fear, and Mistrust in Kenya's White Highlands

Empirical study of long-run effects of exposure to clientelist land reforms on social discord in Kenya.

AWARDS, FUNDING, AND SCHOLARSHIPS

IRC: Funding for CIES 2024 and BAICE 2024 conferences	2024
LMU VAC: Alumni Prize for Young Economists	2023
DAAD: Scholarship for Master Studies	2020
Erasmus+: Study Abroad Grant	2015

MEMBERSHIPS AND SERVICE

Member: Comparative and International Education Society (CIES)	2024-Present
Mentor: Malengo, Uganda-Germany Programme	2024-Present

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

2024: CIES, University of Edinburgh CAS and CeSaR, ASAUK, BAICE

SKILLS

Quant analysis: Stata (advanced), QGIS (advanced), Python (intermediate), R (intermediate) **Qual analysis:** Natural Language Processing (NLP) in Python (NLTK) and R (Quanteda), NVivo **Field research:** design tools, program surveys, train enumerators, draft budgets, manage clients **Languages:** English (native), French (intermediate), German (intermediate), Turkish (intermediate)

PERSONAL

Citizenship: dual citizen of Ireland and the UK (London is home)

References available on request